

BIOSTATISTICIAN · DATA SCIENTIST

Geneva, Switzerland - B Work Permit

【 (+41) 78 228 16 28 ☐ andres.acunamarroquin@gmail.com ☐ Andres-AM ☐ Andrés Acuña

Profile

With over 5 years of experience in R programming and statistical analysis, my passion lies in applying these skills to analyze datasets and extract valuable insights. Strong communication abilities complement my technical expertise, enabling effective collaboration and knowledge sharing.

Skills_

Programming R programming with 5+ years of experience, Base R, Tidyverse, ggplot2, dplyr, purr, Other

programming languages: Bash, Python, MATLAB, Typst and SQL

Data Analysis Experimental design and statistical analysis plans, t-tests, ANOVA (analysis of variance), Sur-

vival analysis, prediction, Sample size calculation and hypothesis testing

Data Visualisation Interactive dashboards using Shiny Apps, **R markdown/Quarto report writing**

Data Quality Developping and implementing Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs), Computerized

System Validation in the Biotechnology industry, GMP, GAMP5 guidelines, ISO 13485 re-

quirements for data handling, Good Clinical Practice (GCP)

Version Control Git and SVN for code management, Data and code documentation

Bioinformatics in-silico testing of qPCR primers and probes against DNA databases, parallel processing to

enhance speed, bioconductor

Spoken Languages English, French and Spanish: Fluent, German: level A2

Experience _

Principal Biostatistician

Marseille, France

VERACYTE INC.

05.2019 - 08.2022

- Provided statistical counseling to up to five teams/clients developing biotechnology products, ensuring timely completion despite overlapping deadlines.
- Conducted statistical planning and analysis to evaluate the performance of qPCR kits, leading to 10 successful kit submissions compliant with in-vitro diagnostic regulation.
- Developed and deployed three interactive web applications (Shiny Apps) and two R packages for customized solutions, including data visualization, automated calculations, and reproducible results, in order to optimize data analysis.
- Validated two in-house developed computerized systems using the computerized system validation process in accordance with GAMP5 guidelines, collaborating closely with multidisciplinary teams including Quality Assurance and IT.
- Effectively led a three-member biostatistics team to ensure timely delivery of high-quality reports and results.
- Designed a bioinformatics pipeline for in silico testing of biological reactions using DNA databases, focusing on process optimisation for enhanced efficiency and speed.

Statistician
INSTITUT IMAGE

Chalon sur Saône, France

• Developed and executed a phobia therapy effectiveness evaluation on study participants.

Conducted statistical analysis to evaluate the effectiveness of a phobia therapy.

Software Developer (MATLAB)

Montpellier, France

EUROPEAN CENTRE FOR RESEARCH ON HUMAN MOVEMENT

04.2015 - 07.2015

03.2016 - 07.2016

- Developed a brain-computer interface utilizing an EEG headset to investigate brain wave patterns through time series analysis.
- Established integration between hardware and software components to extract and analyze signals effectively.

Personal Projects _____

Statistical Report

Andres-AM/report-example

DESIGNER/DEVELOPER

- Example of statistical report using LATEX, Rmarkdown, ggplot2
- Web page link here

Survival Analysis

Andres-AM/survival-analysis

DESIGNER/DEVELOPER

- A brief step-by-step survival analysis conducted in R
- Used tools include quarto, ggsurvfit, survival, plotly, ggplot2, knitr
- Quarto report link here

WeightTrackeR

Andres-AM/WeightTrackR

DESIGNER/DEVELOPER

- A Shiny App for weight tracking and data visualization deployed with Shinyapps.io
- Used tools include modelr, dplyr, purr, shiny, lubridate, plotly, DT, and rsconnect
- Shiny App link here

NutriPlot Andres-AM/NutriPlot

DESIGNER/DEVELOPER

- Scatter plot representation for optimized food selection using Quarto
- Used tools include dplyr, ggplot2, plotly, DT, quarto
- Report link here

Analysis of Newspaper headlines

we-data-ch/globlization_hackaton_training

DESIGNER/DEVELOPER

Sep. 2022 - Present

- Newspaper headlines analysis from www.20min.ch
- Used tools: scoring systems, quarto reporting, DT, crosstalk, plotly
- Report link here

TFScrappeR

Andres-AM/TFScrappeR

DESIGNER/DEVELOPER

Sep. 2022 - Present

- Web scraping tool designed to retrieve and summarize the most recent case laws from the Swiss Federal Supreme Court
- Tools used include **llama3**, dplyr, rvest, polite, purr
- Shiny App link here

Education

University of Montpellier

Montpellier, France

MSc. Health device engineering

2014 - 2016

• Data analysis & statistics, mathematical engineering, signal and image processing

University of Montpellier

Montpellier, France

BSc. BIOTECHNOLOGIES

2011 - 2014

• Cellular and molecular biology, genetics, microbiology

Interests _____

- Member of the **WeData Association** (UNIGE) in data science and computer science.
- Winner of the Public Prize (19.06.24) at the Cultural Globalization Hackathon, Geneva.
- Presented an introductory Data Science video on data quality, in collaboration with the University of Geneva.